Alfred Adler Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Alfred Adler Papers 1888-1975 (bulk 1928-1937)
MSS82306
Adler, Alfred, 1870-1937
900 items 5 containers plus 1 oversize 2.15 linear feet 4 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Psychologist. Chiefly letters written by Adler to his wife and children, including also drafts of a book, articles, lectures, an appointment book, notes, reports, certificates, clippings, printed matter, and photographs relating to Adler's career as a psychologist.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Adler family.; Adler, Alfred, 1870-1937.; Adler, Raissa Epstein--Correspondence.; Allen, G. Margery--Correspondence.; Einstein, Albert, 1879-1955--Correspondence.; Freud, Sigmund, 1856-1939.
Subjects
Psychology.
Occupations
Psychologists.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The papers of Alfred Adler, psychologist, were given to the Library of Congress by his son, Kurt A. Adler, and daughter, Alexandra Adler, between 1973 and 1995. Several items were purchased in 1974 and 1999.
Transfers
Sigmund Freud's Psychopathologie des Alltagslebens, inscribed by Freud to Adler, has been transferred to the Rare Book and Special Collections Division where it is identified as part of the Alfred Adler Papers.
Related Material
Related collections in the Manuscript Division include the
Alfred Adler Papers in the Sigmund Freud Collection
.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Alfred Adler are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of part of these papers is available on four reels. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition as available.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1870, Feb. 7 Born, Vienna, Austria
1895 Graduated, University of Vienna Medical School, Vienna, Austria
1895-1897 Gained clinical experience working in the Polyclinic, Vienna, Austria
1897-1927 Private practice, Vienna, Austria
1897 Married Raissa Timofeivna Epstein
1902 Joined Sigmund Freud's Psychological Wednesday Society, Vienna, Austria
1907 Published Studie über die Minderwertigkeit von Organen. Berlin: Urban & Schwarzenber
1910 President, Vienna Psychoanalytic Society
1911 Resigned from the Vienna Psychoanalytic Society Founded the Society for Free Psychoanalytic Study
1912 Published Über den Nervösen Charakter. Wiesbaden: J. F. Bergmann
1914 Founded the Society for Individual Psychology and its journal, Zeitschrift für Individualpsychologie Published with Carl Furtmüller Heilen und Bilden; Ärzlich-Pädagogische Arbeiten des Vereins für Individualpsychologie. Munich: Ernst Reinhardt
1916-1918 Served as a physician in the Austrian army
1920 Established a network of child guidance clinics attached to public schools, Vienna, Austria Appointed director, Individual Psychological Clinic for Problem Children, Franz-Josef Ambulatorium, Vienna, Austria
1924 Published Praxis und Theorie der Individualpsychologie. Munich: J. F. Bergmann
1926 First American lecture tour
1927 Published Menschenkenntnis. Leipzig: Hirzel
1928 Conducted a course on individual psychology, New School for Social Research, New York, N.Y.
1929 Published Problems of Neurosis: A Book of Case Histories. London: Kegan Paul, Trench Truebner & Co.
1929-1930 Visiting Professor, University Extension, and director of child-guidance clinic, Columbia University, New York, N.Y.
1930 Resigned from Columbia University and opened the Advisory Council of Individual Psychology clinic at the Community Church, New York, N.Y. Published Guiding the Children on the Principles of Individual Psychology. New York: Greenberg
1932 Visiting Professor of Medical Psychology, Long Island College of Medicine, Brooklyn, N.Y. Established the Adler Medical Psychology Clinic, Brooklyn, N.Y.
1937, May 28 Died, Aberdeen, Scotland
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Alfred Adler (1870-1937) span the years 1888-1975, with the bulk of material dating from 1928 to 1937. The papers contain correspondence, lectures, articles, manuscript of a book, an appointment book, patient case studies and record books, reports, notes, photographs, certificates, clippings, and printed matter. The major part of the collection consists of letters written by Adler to his wife and children between 1897 and 1937 and drafts of lectures and articles, many of which Adler wrote while residing in the United States. Correspondence with people outside the Adler family includes a letter written by Albert Einstein in 1937 comparing the theories of Sigmund Freud and Adler.
A small amount of material was added to the collection in 1996 and 2001. The addition includes, among other items, letters from Adler to a former student, G. Margery Allen, a letter from John Haynes Holmes concerning the relocation of Adler's clinic to the Community Church in New York City, congratulatory letters on Adler's sixtieth birthday, drafts of six lectures, and correspondence concerning Adler's death. An undated note by Adler concerning a patient and a photograph of Adler were added in 2001.
A microfilm edition of the first three containers is available. Patient record books and material added to the collection in 1996 and 2001 have not been filmed.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged by type of material.
http://lccn.loc.gov/mm83082306
Container List
Available on microfilm. Shelf no. 20,322
- Appointment book, 1937 (Box 1, Reel 1)
- General correspondence, 1891-1970, undated, (10 folders) (Box 1, Reel 1)
- Lectures (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - 1921 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - 1928-1930, (2 folders) (Box 1, Reel 2)
  - 1931-1936, undated, (4 folders) (Box 2, Reel 2)
  - "Any Marriage Can Succeed: An Interview with Dr. Alfred Adler," by Helena Huntington Smith, undated (Box 2, Reel 2)
  - "Aerztekursus im Urbankrankenhaus," undated (Box 2, Reel 2)
- Writings file (Box 2, Reel 2)
  - Book, The General System of Individual Psychology, undated (Box 2, Reel 2)
    - Chapters 1-7 (Box 2, Reel 2)
    - Chapters 8-13 (Box 2, Reel 3)
  - Articles in English (Box 2, Reel 3)
    - Bashfulness, undated (Box 2, Reel 3)
    - "A Brief Comparison of Individual Psychology and Psycho-Analysis," undated (Box 2, Reel 3)
    - Childhood and youth, undated (Box 2, Reel 3)
    - Courage, undated (Box 2, Reel 3)
    - "Fortunetelling," undated (Box 2, Reel 3)
    - "Fortunetelling," undated (Box 2, Reel 3)
    - "Homosexuality," undated (Box 2, Reel 3)
    - Neurosis, undated (Box 2, Reel 3)
    - "Preface" for Waslaw Nijinsky's autobiography, undated (not used) (Box 3, Reel 3)
    - "The Problem of Crime," undated (Box 3, Reel 3)
    - "Psychiatric Aspects Regarding Individual and Social Disorganization," 1936 (Box 3, Reel 3)
    - "The Technique of Treatment," undated (Box 3, Reel 3)
    - "Psychological Aspects in a Time of Economic Crisis," 1934 (Box 3, Reel 3)
    - "Seven Men and a House, A Study of the Inferiority Complex," undated (Box 3, Reel 3)
  - Articles and lectures in German, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3, Reel 3)
- Patient case studies, 1928-1935, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3, Reel 3)
- Reports of medical meetings, 1928-1932, undated (Box 3, Reel 3)
- Miscellany (Box 3, Reel 3)
  - Certificates, passport, photographs, naturalization papers, etc., 1888-1937, 1950, undated (Box 3, Reel 3)
  - Notes and memoranda, 1897-1938, 1975, undated (Box 3, Reel 3)
  - Printed matter, 1933-1937, undated (Box 3, Reel 3)
  - Clippings, 1930-1937, 1970, undated (Box 3, Reel 4)
- Patient record books, 1903-1907, (2 vols.) (Box 4)
- Addition (Box 5)
  - Allen, G. Margery, 1930-1937 (Box 5)
  - Death of Adler, 1937 (Box 5)
  - General correspondence, 1930-1938, undated (Box 5)
  - Lectures, undated (Box 5)
    - "Advice to the Teacher" (Box 5)
    - "Children's Case-Histories and Their Interpretation" (Box 5)
    - "Compulsion Neurosis" (Box 5)
    - "Drunkards and Drug-Addicts" (Box 5)
    - "How the Child Selects His Symptoms" (Box 5)
    - "The Structure of Neurosis" (Box 5)
  - Medical licenses, 1934-1937 (Box 5)
  - Note by Adler concerning a patient, undated (Box 5)
  - Photograph of Adler, undated (Box 5)
  - Printed matter, 1966, undated (Box 5)
  - Sixtieth birthday, 1930 (Box 5)
    - Certificate of honorary citizenship, Vienna, Austria See Oversize (Box 5)
    - Congratulatory letters (3 folders) (Box 5)
  - Stoker, Richard, String Quartet No. 3, Op. 36 "Adlerian," 1967-1970 (Box 5)
- Oversize (Box OV 1)
  - Addition (Box OV 1)
    - Sixtieth birthday (Box OV 1)
      - Certificate of honorary citizenship, Vienna, Austria, 1930 (Container 5) (Box OV 1)